Chapter 30 The more I knew of the inmates of more house, the better I liked them.
In a few days I had so far recovered my health
that I could sit up all day and walk out sometimes.
I could join with Diana and Mary in all their occupations, converse with them as
much as they wished, and aid them when and where they would allow me.
There was a reviving pleasure in this intercourse,
of a kind now tasted by me for the first time.
The pleasure arising from perfect congeniality of tastes, sentiments and principles.
I like to read what they like to read, what they enjoyed, delighted me,
what they approved, I reverenced.
They loved their sequestered home.
I too, in the grey small antique structure, with its low roof, its lattice
casements, its maulering walls, its avenue of aged furs,
all grown a slant under the stress of mountain winds.
It's garden, dark with you and holly, and where no
flowers but of the hardiest species would bloom.
Found a charm both potent and permanent.
They clung to the purple moors behind and around their dwelling, to the hollow veil
into which the pebbly bridlepath leading for their gate
descended, and which wound between fern banks first.
And then amongst a few of the wildest little pasture fields that ever bordered a
wilderness of heath, or gave sustenance to a flock of gray moorland sheep,
with their little mossy-faced lambs.
They clung to this scene, I say, with a perfect enthusiasm of attachment.
I could comprehend the feeling, and share both its strength and truth.
I saw the fascination of the locality.
I felt the consecration of its loneliness.
My eye feasted on the outline of swell and sweep, on the wild coloring communicated
to ridge and del by moss, by heathbell, by flower-sprinkled
turf, by brilliant bracken and mellow granite crag.
These details were just to me what they were to
them, so many pure and sweet sources of pleasure.
The strong blast and the soft breeze, the rough and the halcyon day,
the hours of sunrise and sunset, the moonlight and the clouded night,
developed for me in these regions, the same attraction as for them,
wound round my faculties, the same spell that entranced theirs.
In doors we agreed equally well.
They were both more accomplished and better read than I was.
But with eagerness, I followed in the path of knowledge they had trodden before me.
I devoured the books they lent me.
Then it was full satisfaction to discuss with them
in the evening what I had perused during the day.
Thought fitted thought, opinion met opinion.
We coincided in short perfectly.
If in our trio there was a superior and a leader, it was Diana.
Physically she far excelled me, she was handsome, she was vigorous.
In her animal spirits there was an affluence of life and certainty of flow,
such as excited my wonder, while it baffled my comprehension.
I could talk a while when the evening commenced,
but the first gush of vivacity and fluency gone.
I was feigned to sit on a stool at Diana's feet, to rest my head on her knee,
and listen alternately to her and Mary, while they
sounded thoroughly the topic on which I had but touched.
Diana offered to teach me German.
I liked to learn of her.
I saw the part of instructor is pleased and suited her.
That of scholar pleased and suited me no less.
Our nature's dovetailed, mutual affection of the strongest kind was the result.
They discovered I could draw.
Their pencils and color boxes were immediately at my service.
My skill, greater in this one point than theirs, surprised and charmed them.
Mary would sit and watch me by the hour together.
Then she would take lessons and a docile, intelligent, assiduous pupil she made.
Thus occupied, and mutually entertained, days passed like hours and weeks like days.
As to Mr. Sinjin, the intimacy which had arisen so naturally
and rapidly between me and his sisters did not extend to him.
One reason of the distance yet observed between
us was that he was comparatively seldom at home.
A large proportion of his time appeared devoted to visiting the sick and poor
among the scattered population of his parish.
No weather seemed to hinder him in these pastoral excursions.
Rain or fair, he would, when his hours of morning study were over.
Take his hat.
And followed by his father's old pointer,
Carlo, go out on his mission of love or duty.
I scarcely know in which light he regarded it.
Sometimes, when the day was very unfavorable, his sisters would expostulate.
He would then say with a peculiar smile, more solemn than cheerful.
And if I let a gust of wind or a sprinkling of rain turn me aside from
these easy tasks, what preparation would such
sloth be for the future I propose to myself?
Diana and Mary's general answer to this question was a
sigh, and some minutes of apparently mournful meditation.
But besides his frequent absences, there was another barrier to friendship with him.
He seemed of a reserved, and abstracted, and even of a brooding nature.
Zealous in his ministerial labours, blameless in his life and habits,
he yet did not appear to enjoy that mental serenity, that inward content,
which should be the reward of every sincere Christian and practical philanthropist.
Often, of an evening, when he sat at the window his desk and papers before him,
he would cease reading or writing, rest his chin on his hand, and deliver
himself up, to I know not what course of thought, but that it was perturbed and
exciting might be seen in the frequent flash and changeful dilation of his eye.
I think more over, that nature was not to him
that treasury of delight it was to his sisters.
He expressed once and but once in my hearing, a strong sense of the rugged
charm of the hills, and an inborn affection for
the dark roof and horny walls, he called his home.
But there was more of gloom than pleasure in the tone and words in which the
sentiment was manifested, and never did he seem to
roam the moors for the sake of their soothing silence.
Never seek out or dwell upon the thousand peaceful delights they could yield.
In communicative as he was, some time elapsed
before I had an opportunity of gauging his mind.
I first got an idea of its caliber when I
heard him preach in his own church at Morton.
I wish I could describe that sermon, but it is past my power.
I cannot even render faithfully the effect it produced on me.
It began calm, and indeed, as far as delivery and pitcher voice went,
it was calm to the end.
An earnestly felt, yet strictly restrained zeal breathed soon
in the distinct accents and prompted the nervous language.
This grew to force, compressed, condensed, controlled.
The heart was thrilled, and the mind astonished by the power of the preacher,
neither was softened.
Throughout, there was a strange bitterness, an absence of consolatory
gentleness, stern illusions to Calvinistic doctrines, election predestination,
reprobation, were frequent.
And each reference to these points sounded like a sentence pronounced for doom.
When he had done, instead of feeling better, calmer, more enlightened by his
discourse, I experienced an inexpressible sadness.
For it seemed to me, I know not whether equally so to others, that the eloquence
to which I had been listening had sprung from a depth where lay turbid of
disappointment, where moved troubling impulses of
insatiate yearnings and disquieting aspirations.
I was sure, Syngen Rivers, pure lived conscientious zealous as he was,
had not yet found that piece of God, which passeth all understanding.
He had no more found it, I thought, than had I, with my concealed and wracking
regrets for my broken idol and lost elicium.
Regrets to which I have latterly avoided referring, but
which possessed me and tyrannized over me ruthlessly.
Meantime, a month was gone.
Diana and Mary were soon to leave more house and return
to the far different life and scene which awaited them.
As governesses in a large, fashionable south of England city, where each held a
situation in families by whose wealthy and haughty members, they were regarded only
as humble dependents, and who neither knew nor sought out their innate excellences,
and appreciated only their acquired accomplishments as they appreciated the
skill of their cook, or the taste of their waiting-woman.
Mr. Syngen had said nothing to me yet about the employment he had promised to
obtain for me, yet it became urgent that I should have a vocation of some kind.
One morning, being left alone with him a few minutes in the parlour, I ventured to
approach the window recess which is table chair and desk consecrated as a kind of
study, and I was going to speak, though not very well knowing in what words
to frame my inquiry, for it is at all times difficult to break the ice of
reserve, glassing over such natures as his, when he saved me the trouble,
by being the first to commence a dialogue, looking up as I drew near.
You have a question to ask of me, he said.
Yes, I wish to know whether you have heard of
any service I can offer myself to undertake.
I found or devised something for you three weeks ago, but as you seemed both useful
and happy here, as my sisters had evidently become attached to you,
and your society gave them unusual pleasure, I deemed it inexperient to break
in on your mutual comfort till their approaching
departure from marsh end should render yours necessary.
And they will go in three days now, I said, yes, and when they go,
I shall return to the parsinage at Morton.
Hanna will accompany me, and this old house will be shut up.
I waited a few moments, expecting he would go on with the subject first broached,
but he seemed to have entered another train of reflection.
His look denoted abstraction from me and my business.
I was obliged to recall him to a theme which was of
necessity one of close and anxious interest to me.
What is the employment you had in view, Mr. Rivers?
I hope this delay will not have increased the difficulty of securing it.
Oh, no, since it is an employment which depends only
on me to give and you to accept, he again paused.
There seemed a reluctance to continue.
I grew impatient, a restless movement or two, and an eager and exacting glance
fastened on his face, conveyed the feeling to him as
effectively as words could have done, and with less trouble.
You need be in no hurry to hear, he said.
Let me frankly tell you I have nothing eligible or profitable to suggest.
Before I explain, recall if you please my notice clearly given that if I helped you,
it must be as the blind man would help the lame.
I am poor, for I find that when I have paid my father's debts, all the patrimony
remaining to me will be this crumbling range, the row of scatheed furs behind,
and the patch of morish soil with the u -trees and hollybushes in front.
I am obscure, Rivers is an old name, but of the three sole descendants of the
race, two earn the dependence crossed among strangers, and the third considers
himself an alien from his native country, not only for life, but in death.
Yes, and deems, and is bound to deem, himself honoured by the lot, and aspires,
but after the day, when the cross of separation from fleshly ties shall be laid
on his shoulders, and when the head of that church militant of whose humblest
members he is one shall give the word, rise, follow me.
Sinjin said these words, as he pronounced his sermons, with a quiet, deep voice,
with an unflushed cheek, and a co -rascating radiance of glance, he resumed.
And since I am myself poor and obscure, I can
offer you but a service of poverty and obscurity.
You may even think it degrading, for I see now your habits have been what
the world calls refined, your tastes leaned to the ideal, and your society has
at least been amongst the educated, but I consider
that no service degrades which can better our race.
I hold that the more arid and unreclaimed the soil where the Christian laborers'
task of tillage is appointed him, the scantier the mead his toil brings,
the higher the honour.
His, under such circumstances, is the destiny of the pioneer,
and the first pioneers of the gospel were the apostles.
Their captain was Jesus, the Redeemer, himself.
Well, I said, as he again paused, proceed.
He looked at me before he proceeded.
Indeed, he seemed leisurely to read my face, as if
its features and lines were characters on a page.
The conclusions drawn from this scrutiny, he
partially expressed in his succeeding observations.
I believe you will accept the post I offer you, said he, and hold it for a while.
Not permanently, though.
Any more than I could permanently keep the narrow and narrowing, the tranquil,
hidden office of English country incumbent, for in your nature is an alloy,
as detrimental to repose as that in mine, though of a different kind.
Do explain, I urged, when he halted once more.
I will.
And you shall hear how poor the proposal is, how trivial, how cramping,
I shall not stay long at Morton, now that my
father is dead, and that I am my own master.
I shall leave the place, probably in the course of a 12-month, but while I do stay,
I will exert myself to the utmost for its improvement.
Morton, when I came to it two years ago, had no school.
The children of the poor were excluded from every hope of progress.
I established one for boys.
I mean now to open a second school for girls.
I have hired a building for the purpose, with a cottage
of two rooms attached to it, for the mistress's house.
Her salary will be 30 pounds a year.
Her house is already furnished, very simply, but
sufficiently by the kindness of a lady, Miss Oliver.
The only daughter of the sole rich man in my parish, Mr. Oliver, the proprietor of a
needle factory and iron foundry in the valley.
The same lady pays for the education and clothing of an orphan from the workhouse.
On condition that she shall aid the mistress in such menial offices connected
with her own house and the school, as her occupation of
teaching will prevent her having time to discharge in person.
Will you be this mistress?
He put the question rather hurriedly.
He seemed half to expect an indignant or at least a disdainful rejection of the offer.
Not knowing all my thoughts and feelings, though guessing some,
he could not tell in what light the lot would appear to me.
In truth, it was humble, but then it was sheltered, and I wanted a safe asylum.
It was plotting.
But then, compared with that of a governess in a rich house, it was independent.
And the fear of servitude with strangers entered my soul like iron.
It was not ignoble, not unworthy, not mentally degrading.
I made my decision.
I thank you for the proposal, Mr. Rivers, and I accept it with all my heart.
But you comprehend me, he said.
It is a village school.
Your scholars will be only poor girls, cottages, children at the best,
farmers, daughters.
Knitting, sowing, reading, writing, ciphering will be all you will have to teach.
What will you do with your accomplishments?
What?
With the largest portion of your mind, sentiments, tastes.
Save them till they are wanted.
They will keep.
You know what you undertake then.
I do, he now smiled, and not a bitter or a sad
smile, but one well pleased and deeply gratified.
And when will you commence the exercise of your function?
I will go to my house tomorrow and open the school if you like next week.
Very well, so be it.
He rose and walked through the room.
Standing still, he again looked at me.
He shook his head.
What do you disapprove of, Mr. Rivers?
I asked.
You will not stay at Morton Long.
No, no.
Why?
What is your reason for saying so?
I read it in your eye.
It is not of that description which promises
the maintenance of an even tenor in life.
I am not ambitious.
He started at the word ambitious.
He repeated, no.
What made you think of ambition?
Who is ambitious?
I know I am.
But how did you find it out?
I was speaking of myself.
Well, if you are not ambitious, you are, he paused.
What?
I was going to say impassioned.
But perhaps you would have misunderstood the word and been displeased.
I mean, that human affections and sympathies have a most powerful hold on you.
I am sure you cannot long be content to pass your leisure in solitude,
and to devote your working hours to a monotonous labour wholly void of stimulus.
Any more than I can be content, he added with emphasis.
To live here buried in morass, pent in with mountains, my nature that God
gave me contravened, my faculties, heaven bestowed, paralysed, made useless.
You hear now how I contradict myself.
I, who preached contentment with a humble lot, and justified the vocation even of
hewers of wood and drawers of water in God's service, I, his ordained minister,
almost rave in my restlessness.
Well, propensities and principles must be reconciled by some means.
He left the room.
In this brief hour, I had learnt more of him than in the whole previous month,
yet still he puzzled me.
Diana and Mary Rivers became more sad and silent as the
day approached for leaving their brother and their home.
They both tried to appear as usual, but the sorrow they had to struggle
against was one that could not be entirely conquered or concealed.
Diana intimated that this would be a different
parting from any they had ever yet known.
It would probably,
as far he will sacrifice all to his long framed resolves, she said.
Natural affection and feelings more potent still.
Sinjin looks quiet, Jane, but he hides a fever in his vitals.
You would think him gentle, yet in some things he is inexorable as death.
And the worst of it is, my conscience will hardly
permit me to dissuade him from his severe decision.
Certainly I cannot for a moment blame him for it.
It is right, noble, Christian, yet it breaks my heart.
And the tears gushed to her fine eyes.
Mary bent her head low over her work.
We are now without father.
We shall soon be without home and brother.
She murmured.
At that moment, a little accident supervened, which seemed decreed by fate
purposely to prove the truth of the adage that misfortunes never come singly,
and to add to their distress is the vexing
one of the slip between the cup and the lip.
Sinjin passed the window reading a letter.
He entered.
Our uncle John is dead, said he.
Both the sisters seemed struck, not shocked or appalled.
The tidings appeared in their eyes rather momentous than afflicting.
Dead?
repeated Diana.
Yes, she riveted a searching gaze on her brother's face.
And what then she demanded in a low voice?
What then died he replied, maintaining a marble immobility of feature?
What then?
Why nothing?
Read.
He threw the letter into her lap.
She glanced over it and handed it to Mary.
Mary perused it in silence and returned it to her brother All three looked at each
other and all three smiled, a dreary, pensive smile enough.
Our men, we can yet live, said Diana at last.
At any rate, it makes us no worse off than we were before remarked Mary.
Only it forces rather strongly on the mind the picture of what might have been,
said Mr. Rivers, and contrasts it somewhat too vividly with what is.
He folded the letter, locked it in his desk and again went out.
For some minutes no one spoke.
Diana then turned to me.
Jane, you will wander at us in our mysteries, she said.
And think us hard-hearted beings, not to be more
moved at the death of so near a relation as an uncle.
But we have never seen him or known him.
He was my mother's brother, my father and he quarreled long ago.
It was by his advice that my father risked most of
his property in the speculation that ruined him.
Mutual recrimination passed between them.
They parted in anger and were never reconciled.
My uncle engaged afterwards in more prosperous undertakings.
It appears he realized a fortune of 20,000 pounds.
He was never married and had no near kindred but ourselves
and one other person, not more closely related than we.
My father always cherished the idea that he would
atone for his error by leaving his possessions to us.
That letter informs us that he has bequeathed every penny to the other
relation, with the exception of 30 guineas to be divided between Sinjin, Diana and
Mary Rivers, for the purchase of three morning rings.
He had a right, of course, to do as he pleased.
And yet a momentary damp is cast on the spirits by the receipt of such news.
Mary and I would have esteemed ourselves rich with a thousand pounds each,
and to Sinjin such as some would have been valuable,
for the good it would have enabled him to do.
This explanation given, the subject was dropped, and no further
reference made to it by either Mr. Rivers or his sisters.
The next day I left Marsh End for Morton, the day
after, Diana and Mary quitted it for distant B.
In a week, Mr. Rivers and Hannah repaired to the
Parsonage, and so the old Grange was abandoned.